"Risks and Benefits of
Nicotinamide Riboside (NR), a NAD+ Booster"
NR and NMN seem to be more promising
NAD+ precursors than NA or NAM,
since they don’t cause flushing
nor do they directly inhibit sirtuins.
In mice, NR and NMN both
raised liver NAD+ levels,
but of the two, only NR significantly
raised NAD+ in the muscles.
Also, NR is so far the only NAD+ booster
shown to prolong the lifespan of mice.
There have been at least
10 clinical trials of NR,
most showing it can boost human
blood levels of NAD+ by up to 168%.
Note, though, that most doses
used exceeded 300 mg,
which is the daily dose
approved as safe
by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration
and European Food Safety Authority.
At the approved dose, blood NAD+ is
boosted more on the order of 50 to 60%,
but no dose was found to affect NAD+ levels
in human muscle (compared to placebo).
The greater preponderance
of human bioavailability
and safety data for
NR compared to NMN
has led some to proclaim NR
as the preferred NAD+ precursor.
And, by some, I mean employees
of a chemical company
that produces NR for supplements.
The question after all
of these human NR trials
is have any of them
shown clinical benefit?
Sadly, no.
Let’s go through the alphabet.
After accounting for
multiple testing,
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials of NR
in middle-aged or older adults failed to find
any significant benefit over placebo
for artery stiffness or
artery function, BAT activation,
blood pressure, blood sugar control,
body weight,
cardiac energy or ejection fraction,
fat burning,
fatty liver, exercise capacity,
fatigue,
insulin sensitivity,
metabolic flexibility,
metabolic health,
metabolic rate,
mitochondrial function
or biogenesis,
muscle blood flow, upper
or lower body muscle strength,
pancreatic function or the
release of metabolic hormones,
the treatment of Parkinson’s disease
symptoms, or physical performance.
NR-hawking companies claim
NR is anti-inflammatory,
but in their own study, only 3 out of 10
markers of inflammation were affected
compared to placebo,
and a subsequent independent study
using the same dose for twice as long
found zero of 12 markers affected.
Remarkably, the opposite was found for
many of these outcomes in rats and mice.
In rodents, NR does raise
NAD+ levels in muscle,
improving insulin sensitivity
and mitochondrial biogenesis,
and on down much of the list.
Why does NR work in rodents but
appear to almost entirely flop in people?
Some have suggested
inadequate dosing.
The typical dose used
in mouse studies
Was about twice that used
in many human studies,
but a double dose has been
tried in people, to no avail.
Another possibility is sirtuin inhibition by NAM,
the main degradation product of NR.
In fact, based on mouse studies,
NR may metabolize in the gut into NAM or
NA before it even makes it in the bloodstream.
Either way, unlike in mice,
NR can’t seem to elevate
NAD+ in human muscle;
so, no wonder there’s no alteration
of human sirtuin activity.
Maybe that explains
the disparate results.
In fact, the key NAD+ synthesizing
enzyme in human muscle biopsies
was actually suppressed
by NR supplementation.
This doesn’t happen in mice,
but it does in people.
Presumably this downregulation
is an adaptive response
to the unnaturally large flood
of NR coming into the system.
So, what happens when you
stop taking the supplement?
How quickly does your enzyme
activity bounce back?
In mice, not only may
their microbiome affect NR,
but the NR may affect
their microbiome, too.
Some of the benefits of NR
can then be transferred
between mice via
fecal transplants.
So, at least in mice,
some of the benefits of NR
may be due to modulating
the mouse microbiome.
The distinct differences between the
gut flora of humans and rodents
may offer another explanation why
NR works in them, but not us.
Unlike NAM, supplementation with
NR did not increase homocysteine levels,
but one study of a combination of NR
plus a resveratrol analogue called pterostilbene
raised LDL cholesterol high enough to kill
as many as 1 in 40 long-term users.
However, this effect is presumed
to be due to the pterostilbene,
as NR alone has not been shown to raise LDL,
whereas pterostilbene has.
One study did find that NR seems to
cause a small reduction in hematocrit,
hemoglobin, and platelet count in
people within a week of starting it.
This shift towards a
more anemic state
was suggested to account for impaired
exercise performance seen in rats given NR.
However, the 35% drop in performance
did not reach statistical significance.
NR did cause a significant increase
in systemic oxidative stress, however,
and another rodent study
found a worsening of inflammation
and deterioration of
metabolic health,
but if positive effects in rodents
don’t translate to people,
perhaps we shouldn’t expect
that negative ones will either.
Regulatory authorities
from Australia, Canada,
Europe, and the United States
have all authorized NR as safe,
at least up to 300mg a day
(or 230 in pregnant and lactating women).
But the lack of demonstrable clinical benefit
would seem to preclude NR supplementation.